welcome back to a push in under 3
minutes no time for intros let's get
into it so the Mexican-American War just
ended and the US gained a massive chunk
of land this land was known as the
Mexican session but here's the issue
should slavery be allowed in this new
land or not the north proclaimed no the
South however said yes so yeah we have
another political crisis there was an
attempt to settle this issue early with
something called the Wilmont priso this
was a proposal to ban slavery and all
land gain for Mexico it passed in the
house where the North had more
representation but failed in the Senate
where the South had enough power to
block it this failure only made
sectional tensions worse pushing the
country closer to conflict so what would
attempt to solve this issue would be the
Compromise of 1850 but it was in many
ways a messy last ditch attempt to keep
the country from falling apart the guy
behind it you guessed it Henry Clint
this compromise had five parts and they
all tried to balance free enslave State
interests first was California would
become a free state second is that Utah
and New Mexico territories got to theci
side on slavery themselves through
voting third is that the slave trade was
banned in Washington DC fourth was a
stricter Fugitive Slave Act was passed
forcing Northerners to return Escape
slaves and five Texas got paid $10
million to give up some land claims yeah
I don't really understand that one
either the big part to know about this
is the Fugitive Slave Act made
Northerners Furious even if they weren't
abolitionists they hated being forced to
return enslaved people this led to
Massive Resistance like the Underground
Railroad working overtime and northern
states passing personal Liberty laws to
ignore the ACT altogether meanwhile in
the South even though they got some wins
from the compromise they still weren't
happy they wanted an even bigger
guarantee that slavery would expand the
failure of this compromise was easy to
see and this weak compromise is easily
the biggest cause of the Civil War we
have talked about thus far on the screen
now are some AP style questions for this
topic pause
now I'll put the answers on the screen
now I will see you in the next one if
you enjoyed this video please consider
becoming a channel member okay I'm sorry
bye wa